Guide to the Peter Smeallie and Peter Smith photographs, 1980-1990 MS2122
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Peter Smeallie and Peter Smith photographs
1980-1990
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Smith, Peter H.
MS2122
1.75 Linear Feet
The Peter Smeallie and Peter Smith Collection consists of 167 photographs and graphics that were reproduced in the book New Construction for Older Buildings: A Design Sourcebook for Archivists and Preservationists (New York: John Wiley & Sons, 1990), which they co-authored. The collection also contains .25 linear feet of correspondence and releases.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Biographical Note
As of 1995, Peter H. Smeallie was President of Research Opportunities Management, a Virginia consulting firm offering strategic advice on creating research and development programs for universities and other organizations. At the time these photos were donated to Special Collections, Mr. Smeallie, who has a degree in Urban Studies from St. Lawrence University, was affiliated with the National Academy of Sciences. His duties during his twelve years there included directing advisory research studies in areas such as geotechnology, manufacturing, construction technology, and infrastructure and urban systems. While with the Academy, Mr. Smeallie also served as a senior officer of the Building Research Board, and was study director for over 20 major projects. From 1979-82 Mr. Smeallie was Vice President of Thomas Vonier Associates, Inc., an architectural and construction firm. Among his clients were the National Trust for Historic Preservation, the National Building Museum, and the National Park Service. During this time he authored (with J. Eberhard) A Guide to the Federal Government for Design and Building Professionals.
As of 1995, Peter H. Smith was employed by the city of Alexandria, Virginia, where he administered both the Old and Historic Alexandria District, and the Parker-Gray District Boards for the Department of Planning and Zoning. Mr. Smith holds a Ph.D. in American Studies from The George Washington University, and has been active in historic preservation in the Washington area for more than 20 years. Prior to joining the staff of the city of Alexandria, he held positions at the National Trust for Historic Preservation, the Advisory Council for Historic Preservation, and the National Endowment for the Arts. Mr. Smith has served as private consultant on a number of preservation projects and was a founder of the D.C. Preservation League.
Collection Scope and Content
The Peter Smeallie and Peter Smith Collection consists of 167 photographs and graphics that were reproduced in the book New Construction for Older Buildings: A Design Sourcebook for Archivists and Preservationists (New York: John Wiley & Sons, 1990), which they co-authored. The collection also contains .25 linear feet of correspondence and releases.
The Peter Smeallie and Peter Smith Collection of photographs demonstrates the importance of combining old and new buildings in architectural renovation projects. Such designs are aesthetically pleasing in addition to being practical, and became common in the 1980's. Fostered in large part by the historic preservation movement, this mixing of new and old architectural styles is not limited to only historic or significant buildings, as those represented in this collection range from small residential buildings to large office and retail complexes. The photographs visually document a wide range of successful architectural renovations throughout the country, with many of them dealing with the Washington, DC area.
Collection Organization
Organized into two series: Photographs; Correspondence and Releases.
Historic preservation; Historic buildings -- Conservation and restoration; Washington (D.C.); Photographs; George Washington University. American Studies Dept.; George Washington University; Smeallie, Peter H.; George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae
- Correspondence and Releases, 1980-1990; MS2122 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of correspondence and releases.
  The material range in date from 1980-90.
  - Release Forms, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    General note
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1980-1990; MS2122 Series 1; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series consists consists of 167 photographs and graphics that were reproduced in the book New Construction for Older Buildings: A Design Sourcebook for Archivists and Preservationists (New York: John Wiley & Sons, 1990), which Peter Smeallie and Peter Smith co-authored.
  The materials range in date from 1980-90.
  - 1st American Bank Building. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1001 Pennsylvania Avenue. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1001 Pennsylvania Avenue. Washington, District of Columbia. (11th & E Street, NW), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1100 New York Avenue. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1752 N. Street, NW. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1752 N. Street, NW. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1911 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 2000 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 2000 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Atlantic Coastline Building. Washington, District of Columbia. (6th & Pennsylvania Ave, NW), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Carbery School. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Decatur Carriage House. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Demonet Building. Washington, District of Columbia. (Connecticut & M Street, NW), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - East Capitol Car Barn. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - East Capitol Street Car Barn (Main Section). Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Last Capitol Street Car Tarn NE. Washington, District of Columbia., undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Faith Baptist Church. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Festival Market Place (Old Post Office Pavilion). Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Folger Shakespeare Library. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Gallery Row. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Historical Society. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Interior Atrium of The National Press Building. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Lafayette Park (West side). Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Longworth House Office Building. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Madison National Bank Building (M & 29th Street, NW). Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Metropolitan Club. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Metropolitan Club. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - National Academy of Science. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - National Academy of Science (West Wing). Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - National Press Building. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Old Post Office. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Park Road Apartments. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Park Road Apartments. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Residence. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Riggs Bank Building (9th & F Street, NW). Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Riggs National Bank, 14th Street. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Sears House. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - A small sliver of available land on Connecticut Avenue near the White House. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Stables Art Center. Washington, District of Columbia., undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Sumner Square. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Sumner Square. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - United States Capital. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Washington Design Center. Washington, District of Columbia., undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Washington Design Center. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Washington International School (Academic Building). Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Washington International School. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Washington International School. Washington, District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - USF&G Mount Washington Center. Baltimore, Maryland, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - McAuley Hall, USF&G Mount Washington Center. Baltimore, Maryland, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - William Donald Schafer Conservatory and Gardens, Druid Hill Park. Baltimore, Maryland, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - William Donald Schafer Conservatory and Gardens, Druid Hill Park. Baltimore, Maryland, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Castle Center for the Arts. Hyattsville, Maryland, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Castle Center for the Arts (rear view). Hyattsville, Maryland, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Torpedo Factory. Alexandria, Virginia, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Chrysler Museum. Norfolk, Virginia, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Greenbrier Resort. White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Alabama Power Company Headquarters. Birmingham, Alabama, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Alabama Power Company Headquarters. Birmingham, Alabama, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Clocktower, Stanford University. Palo Alto, California, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Levi's Plaza. San Francisco, California, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Levi's Plaza. San Francisco, California, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - San Francisco Gift Center. San Francisco, California, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bonfils Mansion. Denver, Colorado, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Encore Condominium Redevelopment. Denver, Colorado, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sessions Mansion. Bristol, Connecticut, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sessions Mansion. Bristol, Connecticut, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 20 North Michigan Avenue Building. Chicago, Illinois, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 20 North Michigan Avenue Building. Chicago, Illinois, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 116 South Michigan Avenue. Chicago, Illinois, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 116 South Michigan Avenue. Chicago, Illinois, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Historic Newberry Library. Chicago, Illinois, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Leon Mandel Assembly Hall. Chicago, Illinois, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Manufactors Hanover Plaza. Chicago, Illinois, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Manufactors Hanover Plaza. Chicago, Illinois, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Walker Museum/Graduate School of Business. Chicago, Illinois, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Walker Museum/Graduate School of Business. University of Chicago, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Fast College Viditorivirn, DePauw University. Greencastle, Indiana, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - East College Building, DePauw University. Greencastle, Indiana, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Julia Place, Central Courtyard. New Orleans, Louisiana, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Julia Place. New Orleans, Louisiana, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Boston Public Library. Boston, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The Boylston Building. Boston, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Burberry House. Boston, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Charles Street Meeting House. Boston, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Charles Street Meeting House. Boston, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Charles Street Meeting House. Boston, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - China Trade Center. Boston, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Church Court Condominiums. Boston, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Church Court Condominiums. Boston, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Mercantile Wharf Building (Apartment). Boston Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Mercantile Wharf Building. Boston, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Piano Craft Guild. Boston, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - San Marco/Lincoln Wharf. Boston, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - San Marco/Lincoln Wharf. Boston, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Bulfinch Square. Cambridge, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - North and Cabot Houses, Radcliffe Quadrangle, Harvard University. Cambridge, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Former Middlesex County Courthouse. East Cambridge, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Rodman Candleworks. New Bedford, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Rodman Candleworks. New Bedford, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Crown and Eagle Apartments. Uxbridge, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Mary Cooper Jewett Arts Center, Wellesley College. Wellesley, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Cartney-Hunt House. Columbus, Mississippi, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - St. Louis Union Station, Grand Hall. St. Louis, Missouri, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - St. Louis Union Station. St. Louis, Missouri, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Wainwright State Office Building. St. Louis, Missouri, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Main House, Dublin School. Dublin, New Hampshire, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The New Library and Learning Center, Colby-Sawyer College. New London, New Hampshire, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Susan-Colgate Cleveland Library, Colby-Sawyer College. New London, New Hampshire, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - All Saints Parish Church. Peterborough, New Hampshire, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Peterborough Savings Bank. Peterborough, New Hampshire, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Peterborough Savings Bank. Peterborough, New Hampshire, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Van Dorn Mill, Axonometric View. Basking Ridge, New Jersey, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Van Dorn Mill, Offices of Haines Lundberg Waehler. Basking Ridge, New Jersey, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Guernsey Hall. Princeton, New Jersey, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Infill Housing Design Competition. Albany, New York, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Erie Community College, City Campus. Buffalo, New York, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Erie Community College, City Campus. Buffalo, New York, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Goldome Bank for Savings Corporate Headquarters. Buffalo, New York, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Guaranty Building (Prudential Building). Buffalo, New York, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Guaranty Building (Prudential Building). Buffalo, New York, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Guaranty Building (Prudential Building). Buffalo, New York, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Old Post Office, Interior Atrium. Buffalo, New York, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Combined Facility for 19th Precinct and Engine Co., 39 and Ladder Co., 16. New York, New York, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Trinity Church Pedestrian Overpass. New York,-New York, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Oyster Bay Cove. Oyster Bay Cove, New Yolk, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - One Bell Central. Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - One Bell Central. Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Robinson Renaissance Building. Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Mid-Continent Tower. Tulsa. Oklahoma, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Mid-Continent Tower. Tulsa, Oklahoma, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Harrisburg Old City Hall. Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Harrisburg Old City Hall. Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Delaware Aqueduct Bridge. Minisink, New York/Lackawaxen, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - The School House. Mechanicsburg, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - The School House. Mechanicsburg, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Bank Street Court. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - The Chocolate Works. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - The Chocolate Works. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Levis Strauss Offices Site Plan. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - The Wireworks. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - The Wireworks. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - The School House. Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Shadyside Commons. Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Shadyside Commons, Landscaped Courtyard. Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Software Engineering Institute. Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Software Engineering Institute. Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Software Engineering Institute. Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - The Keystone Firehouse. Reading, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - InterMetro Industries Corp. Headquarters. Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - InterMetro Industries Corp. Headquarters. Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Blackstone Falls. Central Falls, Rhode Island, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Davenport, Evans, Hurwitz & Smith Building. Sioux Falls, South Dakota, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Veterans' Administration Hospital Addition and Renovation. Sioux Falls, South Dakota, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - InterFirst II Building. Dallas, Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Hendley Building. Galveston, Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Hendley Building. Galveston, Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Hendley Building. Galveston, Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Springer Building. Galveston, Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Springer Building. Galveston, Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - H.E. Butt Grocery Company Corporate Headquarters. San Antonio, Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - H.E. Butt Grocery Company Corporate Headquarters. San Antonio, Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - The Emily Morgan Hotel. San Antonio, Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - San Antonio Museum of Art. San Antonio, Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - San Antonio Museum of Art. San Antonio, Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Bodega Court. Tacoma, Washington, undated (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Bodega Court. Tacoma, Washington, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Queen's Quay Terminal. Toronto, Ontario, Canada, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)